<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Central Bank Independence on Trym Nohr Fjørtoft</title>
    <link>https://www.trymnf.com/blog/central-bank-independence/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Central Bank Independence on Trym Nohr Fjørtoft</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-US</language>
    <copyright>Copyright © 2025, Trym Nohr Fjørtoft.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 06 Jul 2023 09:49:03 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://www.trymnf.com/blog/central-bank-independence/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Inductive Risk and the Legitimacy of Non-Majoritarian Institutions</title>
      <link>https://www.trymnf.com/publications/inductive-risk-bjps/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.trymnf.com/publications/inductive-risk-bjps/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In political discourse, it is common to claim that non-majoritarian institutions are legitimate because they are technical and value-free. Even though most analysts disagree, many arguments for non-majoritarian legitimacy rest on claims that work best if institutions are, in fact, value-free. This paper develops a novel standard for non-majoritarian legitimacy. It builds on the rich debate over the value-free ideal in philosophy of science, which has not, so far, been applied systematically to political theory literature on non- majoritarian institutions. This paper suggests that the argument from inductive risk, a strong argument against the value-free ideal, (1) shows why a naive claim to value freedom is a poor general foundation for non-majoritarian legitimacy; (2) provides a device to assess the degree of democratic value inputs required for an institution to be legitimate; which (3) shows the conditions under which a claim to technical legitimacy might still be normatively acceptable.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
