<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Border Control on Trym Nohr Fjørtoft</title>
    <link>https://www.trymnf.com/blog/border-control/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Border Control on Trym Nohr Fjørtoft</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-US</language>
    <copyright>Copyright © 2025, Trym Nohr Fjørtoft.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 27 Jun 2023 09:00:00 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://www.trymnf.com/blog/border-control/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Symmetry in the delegation of power as a legitimacy criterion</title>
      <link>https://www.trymnf.com/publications/fjortoft-sandven-jcms/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.trymnf.com/publications/fjortoft-sandven-jcms/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The EU’s power is expanding, calling for reassessments of its normative legitimacy. This article proposes a novel criterion for assessing the EU’s legitimacy: symmetry in the delegation of power. We illustrate the usefulness of this criterion  through an analysis of the European border regime. Existing analyses of the border regime have tended to dismiss it as weak and intergovernmental. We show, to the contrary, that it is both strong and weak. The EU wields significant power in border control but lacks power altogether in immigration policy. This asymmetry has rendered the EU incapable of discharging the moral responsibilities that arise in migration control, posing a novel legitimacy challenge. Finally, we argue that the symmetry criterion generalises and can shed light on the EU’s legitimacy beyond the area of migration.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Legitimizing Role of Expertise in Frontex after the Refugee Crisis</title>
      <link>https://www.trymnf.com/publications/frontex/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.trymnf.com/publications/frontex/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This article explores how the appeal to depoliticized expertise worked to legitimize increased supervisory and executive power to the European Border and Coast Guard Agency, Frontex, after the 2015 refugee crisis. Frontex is an EU agency operating in a highly salient field, removed from hard‐science &amp;ldquo;gold standards&amp;rdquo; of evidence, where member states have been reluctant to delegate power and sovereignty. Through a process‐tracing case study, this article finds that appeals to technical neutrality, quantification, and objective indicators nevertheless were central when a new mandate for the agency was negotiated, giving Frontex unprecedented supervisory and executive power. They were also important resources for member states concerned about Frontex&amp;rsquo;s increased powers. By focusing on an agency at a remove from the natural‐science archetype, this article contributes to the literature on knowledge use in independent agencies. It suggests that technical expertise can be a powerful source of legitimacy even in a field removed from &amp;ldquo;hard&amp;rdquo; science.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
