<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Expertise on Trym Nohr Fjørtoft</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/blog/expertise/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Expertise on Trym Nohr Fjørtoft</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-US</language>
    <copyright>Copyright © 2025, Trym Nohr Fjørtoft.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 17 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/blog/expertise/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>The Legitimizing Role of Expertise in Frontex after the Refugee Crisis</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/frontex/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/frontex/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This article explores how the appeal to depoliticized expertise worked to legitimize increased supervisory and executive power to the European Border and Coast Guard Agency, Frontex, after the 2015 refugee crisis. Frontex is an EU agency operating in a highly salient field, removed from hard‐science &amp;ldquo;gold standards&amp;rdquo; of evidence, where member states have been reluctant to delegate power and sovereignty. Through a process‐tracing case study, this article finds that appeals to technical neutrality, quantification, and objective indicators nevertheless were central when a new mandate for the agency was negotiated, giving Frontex unprecedented supervisory and executive power. They were also important resources for member states concerned about Frontex&amp;rsquo;s increased powers. By focusing on an agency at a remove from the natural‐science archetype, this article contributes to the literature on knowledge use in independent agencies. It suggests that technical expertise can be a powerful source of legitimacy even in a field removed from &amp;ldquo;hard&amp;rdquo; science.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What drives public acceptance of expert agencies?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/what-drives-public-acceptance-of-expert-agencies/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/what-drives-public-acceptance-of-expert-agencies/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This post is written with Asimina Michailidou and was first published at &lt;a href=&#34;https://theloop.ecpr.eu/news-media-and-the-construction-of-eu-technocratic-legitimacy/&#34;&gt;The Loop&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt; It builds on the findings in our &lt;a href=&#34;http://localhost:1313/publications/fjortoft-michailidou-prx/&#34;&gt;PRX article&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;hr&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;As the Covid-19 pandemic has shown, public acceptance of expert agencies is not a given. Nor is scientific expertise a sufficient precondition for an agency’s public legitimacy. To preserve the credibility of democratic governance that relies increasingly on inputs from independent expert bodies, we must understand the conditions under which an expert agency gains the public’s approval.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Beyond expertise: the public construction of legitimacy for EU agencies</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/fjortoft-michailidou-prx/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/fjortoft-michailidou-prx/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;How is the power of independent agencies legitimized? This is a central question in modern democratic societies. Earlier research has privileged technical expertise as the predominant source of legitimacy for such agencies. While recent contributions have challenged this assumption, we have seen few attempts to systematically analyze the conditions under which different sources of legitimacy are established in public discourse. We address this gap by proposing a conceptual framework of four legitimation arguments and test their prevalence through an empirical analysis of the public legitimation of EU agencies. We hypothesize that the prevalence of each argument depends on characteristics of the agency, especially its scientific ‘hardness’ and its public salience. We test our hypotheses in three steps. We first combine automated text classification and qualitative content analysis to analyze Swedish news media coverage of three EU agencies, 2005&amp;ndash;2019. In a third step, we quantitatively analyze aggregated data on the Swedish news coverage of all EU agencies 2005&amp;ndash;2019. We find more technical-expertise discourse in coverage of hard-science agencies, and more political-control discourse where agencies are &amp;ldquo;softer&amp;rdquo; or more salient. Our findings are therefore relevant for ongoing normative and empirical discussions on the legitimacy of independent agencies.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The appeal to expertise in Frontex</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/the-appeal-to-expertise-in-frontex/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/the-appeal-to-expertise-in-frontex/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s a blog post I wrote for the &lt;a href=&#34;https://eutarn.blogactiv.eu/2020/04/10/the-appeal-to-expertise-in-frontex/&#34;&gt;TARN blog&lt;/a&gt; in 2020. It builds on the same ideas and research as my &lt;a href=&#34;http://localhost:1313/publications/frontex/&#34;&gt;Regulation &amp;amp; Governance&lt;/a&gt; piece.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-refugee-crisis-and-its-aftermath&#34;&gt;The refugee crisis and its aftermath&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In 2015, many European states experienced a massive influx of migrants and refugees seeking protection within their borders. The European Refugee crisis was a crisis in many respects&amp;mdash;first and foremost for the people forced to flee their homes, but also for the institution tasked with managing the EU&amp;rsquo;s external borders. That institution is Frontex, the European Border and Coast Guard Agency.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
